Finding Aid for Ferry Family Papers 1758-1989
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Ferry Family (Dexter Ferry) papers
1758-1989
1855-1959
Ferry family.
90118 Aa 2 AC
A pioneer Detroit, Michigan family, established the Ferry Seed Company and other business enterprises, active in civic and cultural affairs. Papers document the family and its business, cultural, political and philanthropic activities.
23.5 linear feet in 25 boxes
7 oversize volumes
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection (Donor No. 7555 ) was donated by Dexter Ferry, III, in the summer of 1988. Additional materials were donated in the spring of 1989 and in 1995.
The collection is open for research.
The Ferry family has long been prominent in the Detroit community; the Ferrys have carved large niches in the local business, philanthropic, and political arenas. The first of the family to arrive on the Detroit scene was Dexter Mason Ferry (1833-1907), who came in 1854 to be employed by the S. Dow Elwood & Co. booksellers. Ferry supplemented his income by working nights for the firm of M.T. Gardner and Company, Seedsmen. Trading on his knowledge of agriculture, sales, and bookkeeping, Ferry quickly rose to the position of partner in the newly named Gardner, Church, and Ferry Seed Co. Increased demand, lower transportation costs to prairie farmers, and sales on the commission system led to the rapid growth of the firm. Ferry eventually gained controlling interest in the concern and formed D.M. Ferry & Co. in 1879; this firm prospered and dominated the national market into the twentieth century. The seed company formed the core of Ferry's business empire and served as a springboard from which he launched other entrepreneurial ventures.
In many ways, Ferry was the quintessential nineteenth- century capitalist, turning an innovative idea and a regional monopoly to his advantage in gaining the edge in the national market. He built on this edge by diversifying, using the seed firm's profits to finance his ventures in other enterprises. He bought real estate in and around Detroit, including the site and building occupied by the Newcomb-Endicott Co. (now part of the J.L. Hudson block) and the Ferry seed farm in Greenfield. As a man of position and means, Ferry was tapped to serve as president of the First National Bank of Detroit, the Union Trust Company, the American Harrow Company, the National Pin Company, the Standard Accident Insurance Company, and the Michigan Fire and Marine Insurance Company. The positions reflected the esteem Ferry enjoyed among his peers in Detroit.
As with many nineteenth century capitalists, Ferry felt an obligation to share a measure of the bounty he enjoyed with society in the form of charity. His noblesse oblige manifested itself in gifts to churches, Olivet College, the University of Michigan, Grace Hospital, and an Art Loan Exhibit that some contend was a lineal forebear of the Detroit Museum of Art, which in time became the Detroit Institute of Art. Ferry also ran true to the patterns of his peers in his staunch affiliation with the Republican party. He served as chairman of the Republican State Central Committee from 1896 to 1898 and was delegate-at-large from Michigan at the Republican National Convention in 1904. In 1900, Ferry answered his party's call and ran for governor; he lost in a heated three-cornered race.
By the time of Dexter Mason Ferry's death in 1907, he had firmly established his family's status among the Detroit elite. His surviving children, Dexter, Jr., Blanche, and Queene, were left to preserve this status and to serve as trustees to the Ferry fortune. Young Ferry served as administrator of the estate and succeeded his father as president of D.M. Ferry & Co. Dexter Ferry, Jr. oversaw the continued growth of the firm through its 1930 merger with the C.C. Morse Co. of San Francisco, a move which secured the continued dominance of the market by the firm. Ferry retired as president of Ferry-Morse in 1941, but continued to serve as chairman of the board until his death in 1959. Ferry, Jr. also filled his father's shoes as president of the Standard Accident Life Insurance Company, the First National Bank of Detroit, the National Pin Company, and American Harrow. He further diversified the Ferry portfolio by serving on the board of the Detroit Trust Company, owning the Crosstown Garage, and investing in the Packard Motor Car Company. This breadth enabled the Ferry family to weather the Great Depression.
In addition to inheriting a measure of his father's business acumen, Ferry, Jr. retained a sense of noblesse oblige. Young Ferry's philanthropic interest was more toward the beaux arts as he was a primary benefactor of the Detroit Institute of Art. He served as president of the Detroit Museum of Art from 1913 to 1917 and headed its Founders Society from 1920 to 1948. Education was highly esteemed by Ferry, Jr.; Lawrenceville prep school, Olivet and Vassar Colleges, and especially the University of Michigan benefited from his generosity. Aside from the arts and education, Ferry's philanthropy reached national and local organizations: the YMCA, the Red Cross, Grace Hospital, the Franklin Settlement, and worthy causes in Grosse Pointe.
Like his father, young Ferry was a lifelong Republican. He was elected to the Michigan House of Representatives in 1901 and served until 1904, working primarily to protect the interests of the University of Michigan. This political experience served him well as a member of the State Board of Education from 1906 to 1912, especially during his tenure as its president after 1908. In 1920, shortly after moving to the village of Grosse Pointe, Ferry was appointed council-man. Ferry was then elected to succeed himself; his involvement in local politics continued until the 1950s. Ferry, Jr. died in December 1959 having achieved a prominence on a par with his father.
The mantle of responsibility for maintaining the family name and honor fell to the third generation of Ferrys in Detroit. The children of Dexter Mason Ferry, Jr.- Dexter, III, W. Hawkins, Edith, and Jeanette- have remained actively involved on the local business and philanthropic scenes.
The Ferry Family Papers are organized in three series, each with several sub-series:
Series I: HISTORICAL AND BACKGROUND, 1758-1989
Biographies, 1896-1957 (Box 1)
Genealogy, 1891-1980 (Box 1)
Histories, 1984-1989 (Box 1)
Materials on Ferry-Mason families, 1758-1886 (Boxes 1-2)
Series II: DEXTER MASON FERRY PAPERS, 1849-1910
Business Interests, 1854-1910 (Boxes 2-4, and 3 oversize volumes)
Business Investments, 1880-1910 (Box 4)
Business Property, 1849-1910 (Boxes 4 and 1 oversize volume)
Personal, 1849-1911 (Boxes 25)
Philanthropies, 1882-1902 (Box 5)
Political, 1892-1903 (Boxes 5 and 1 oversize volume)
Series III: DEXTER MASON FERRY, JR., PAPERS, 1881-1963
Business, 1881-1963 (Boxes 6-10)
Personal, 1884-1960 (Boxes 10-18 and 2 oversize volumes)
Philanthropies, 1890-1959 (Boxes 18-20)
Political, 1899-1959 (Boxes 20-21)
Series IV: Photographs (boxes 21-23)
Series V: Memorabilia and later family materials (box 24)
The Ferry family papers document the rise to prominence of this family who first gained their fortune as seed merchants. The papers also reveal the workings of other Detroit businesses, the development of the Detroit Institute of Arts, turn-of-the-century Michigan politics, and the suburban development of Grosse Pointe. The papers span the years 1758 to 1989 with the bulk of the materials covering 1855 to 1959. The collection consists of: account books, ledgers, journals, and business reports; blue prints, deeds, titles, abstracts, and mortgages; correspondence (business and personal); appointment books, diaries, scrapbooks, and clippings; receipts and tax returns, photographs, and printed miscellanea. It is important to note that the Michigan Historical Collections does not house all extant Ferry materials. The donor, Dexter M. Ferry, III, retains possession of several early account books, ledgers, and journals related to D.M. Ferry & Co.; he also kept some family correspondence and virtually all photographs.
The Ferry family papers arrived at the Michigan Historical Collections in an order based on when the donor reviewed the materials. In the course of reprocessing, this order was altered, and an arrangement assigning primacy to the generation of Ferry who created the document was followed. This reprocessing has resulted in three series: Historical and Background, materials predating Dexter M. Ferry; Dexter M. Ferry; and Dexter M. Ferry, Jr. The few problems presented by overlap between generations are duly noted in the contents list. Within these generational series the materials are arrayed in business, personal, philanthropic, and political subseries. Given the natures of the family and the family business, the researcher should note that murkiness exists between subseries divisions. In general these dividing principles work well. They preserve Dexter M. Ferry, III's original order at the folder level while facilitating access by independent researchers.
The strengths of the Ferry collection are myriad. The family correspondence provide unique insight into a family which grew wealthy but remained close-knit. Especially interesting are the long runs of correspondence between Dexter M. Ferry and his mother, Lucy Ferry Crippen, and Dexter M. Ferry, Jr. and his mother, Addie Miller Ferry. The former run reveals much about the fluid society of late nineteenth-century Detroit, and the latter reflects the pressures of more rigidly defined social strictures. The correspondence between Ferry, Jr. and his sisters, Blanche Ferry Hooker and Queene Ferry Coonley, are illuminating on the handling of the family business in the changing economic climates of the twentieth century.
Some facets of the development of the Detroit business community are well documented as the family invested heavily in local real estate and business. The strengths of the present collection revolve around the Dexter M. Ferry, Jr. materials relating to business and finance in Detroit from 1920 to 1950, particularly the banking community's reaction to the crisis of the Depression. The links between automobile touring, the good roads movement, and the development of ancillary industries to support the burgeoning automotive industry are fairly well documented by Dexter M. Ferry, Jr.'s papers. Young Ferry's close association with the development of the Detroit Institute of Arts is extremely well documented and these papers provide a case study of twentieth century patronage.
A somewhat refracted view of Michigan politics at the turn of the twentieth century is provided through the scrapbooks and clippings on Dexter Ferry's failed campaign in 1900 for governor of the state. The papers are stronger in their documentation of Dexter Ferry, Jr.'s political involvement with the local governance of Grosse Pointe. Here the details of community control are thoroughly covered by correspondence, reports, and minutes.
Subject Terms:
Automobile travel.; Detroit (Mich.); Detroit (Mich.)--Commerce.; Detroit Institute of Arts.; Elections--Michigan--1900.; Ferry family.; Ferry Field (University of Michigan); Ferry-Morse Seed Company.; Grosse Pointe (Mich.)--Politics and government.; Michigan. Legislature. House of Representatives.; National Pin Company.; New York (State); Philanthropists--Michigan--Detroit.; Real property--Michigan--Detroit.; Republican Party (Mich.); Seed industry and trade--Michigan--Detroit.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1891-1900.
Contributors:
Ferry, Dexter Mason, 1833-1907.; Ferry, Dexter Mason, 1872-1959.; Hooker, Blanche Ferry.; Mason, Darius.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Agricultural laborers.; Detroit (Mich.)--Streets.; Farming.; Ferry, Dexter Mason, 1872-1959.; Ferry-Morse Seed Company.; Godfrey Block (Detroit, Mich.); Military art and science.; Seed industry and trade--Michigan--Detroit.
Form and Genre terms:
Business records.; Diaries.; Photographs.; Stereographs.
- Historical Background, 1758-1980
  This series Historical and Background files consists of 14 linear inches of materials arranged alphabetically by type of material: biographies, genealogies, histories, and materials related to the Ferry and Mason families. The biographical and historical materials focus on Dexter Mason Ferry's life and career. The genealogical materials were created to meet the demands of Dexter Mason Ferry, Jr. The bulk of the last subseries is comprised of the Darius Mason diaries, volumes which document the life of a farmer in upstate New York.
  - Biographies of Dexter M. Ferry, 1896-1957
    - Anonymous in Detroit Light Guard, 1896 (Box 1)
    - Catlin, George, 1924-1929 (Box 1)
    - Ferry, Marian, "Dexter M. Ferry: A 19th Century Capitalist", 1957 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous notes, 1900-1948 (Box 1)
  - Genealogy, 1891-1980
    - Ferry family, 1898-1947; 11 folders (Box 1)
    - Hawkins family, 1935-1957; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Miller family, 1927-1933; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Miller/White family, 1980 (Box 1)
    - White family, 1891 (Box 1)
  - Histories, 1984-1989
    - Faulkner, Elizabeth Cooney, 1978
      - "Edith Ferry, 1869-1894" (Box 1)
    - Ferry, Dexter, III, 1984-1989
      - "Ferry-Mason-Miller-Finches", 1984 (Box 1)
      - "Ancestors and Descendants" "History-Good and Bad, 1989-1991" (Box 1)
      - "Visits to History", 1984-1989 (Box 1)
    - Seeger, A., 1988
      - "Seeds of Fortune", 1988 (Box 1)
  - Materials related to Ferry-Mason-Finch families predating Dexter M. Ferry, 1758-1886
    - Carpenter, Stephen, 1758-1813
      - Diary, 1758 (Box 1)
      - Correspondence, 1812-1813 (Box 1)
    - Ferry, Joseph Northrop (poem), 1830 (Box 1)
    - Mason, Darius, 1822-1886
      - Diaries, 1822-1873
        - 1822-1852, 4 volumes; 1 folders (Box 1)
        - 1852-1873, 6 volumes (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous notes, 1857-1886 (Box 2)
    - Mason, Dexter, 1808-1813 (Box 2)
    - Mason, John (list of students in Cheshire, Ma.), 1818 (Box 2)
    - Mason, Timothy, 1776-1787 (Box 2)
    - Schoolmaster (unidentified), 1796 (Box 2)
    - Varick, Abraham, 1798 (Box 2)
- Dexter Mason Ferry Papers, 1849-1910
  This Dexter Mason Ferry Papers series consists of six subseries comprising 4 linear feet. Given Ferry's varied levels of involvement, the business materials are broken down into Business Interests (arranged in a rough chronological order); Business Investments and Business Properties (each of which is arranged alphabetically). The property materials can provide insights to Detroit development to the researcher well versed in local geography. The bulk of the 2 linear feet of the Personal subseries consist of two runs of correspondence (family and general), financial papers, and scrapbooks. The rather abbreviated Philanthropy subseries only hints at the breadth of Ferry's interest in education and the arts. Finally, the linear foot given to the Political subseries is dominated by scrapbooks of newspaper articles regarding Ferry's run for governor.
  - Business Interests, 1854-1910
    - Booksellers correspondence, 1856-1857
      - Elwood, S. Dow, 1856 (Box 2)
      - Howe, William B., 1857 (Box 2)
    - Gardner, Church, and Ferry Seed Co., 1855-1866
      - Bloss and Buell Court Case, 1857 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence, 1855-1866; 5 folders (Box 2)
    - D. M. Ferry & Co., 1867-1908
      - Correspondence, 1867-1895 (Box 2)
        (includes 1867 partnership agreement)
      - Historical materials (H.K. White),1867-1907, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Letterpress books, 1890-1898; 4 volumes (Box 2)
      - Letterpress books, 1899-1911; 6 volumes (Box 3)
        (1906-1911 volume includes rent statements from Newcomb-Endicott Co., 1908-1926)
      - D.M. Ferry & Co. (Bowen's orders), 1898-1899 (Volume 1)
    - Correspondence, 1854-1903; 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Standard Accident Insurance Co., 1884-1899 (Box 4)
    - National Pin Co., 1898-1910
      - Ledgers, account books, articles of incorporation, 1898-1910 (Box 4)
      - Pin companies pool agreements, 1903-1906 (Box 4)
      - National Pin Co. (trial balances), 1902-1911 (Volume 2)
      - National Pin Co. cartoon (Box 24)
    - Account Book (notes payable) (includes D.M. Ferry, Jr. materials), 1885-1920 (Volume 3)
  - Business Investments, 1880-1910
    - American Blower Co., 1897-1899 (Box 4)
    - Detroit and Cleveland Steamship, 1885 (Box 4)
    - Detroit Copper and Brass, 1885-1886 (Box 4)
    - Mesa Improvement/Consolidated Canal, 1899-1910 (Box 4)
    - Newcomb-Endicott, 1880-1910
      - Account book, 1898-1902 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence and accounts, 1895-1897 (Box 4)
      - Leases, 1880-1910; 3 folders (Box 4)
      - Partnership, 1896-1910 (Box 4)
    - Santa Fe, Prescott, and Phoenix R.R., 1894-1909
      - Account book, 1894-1899 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence and receivables, 1896-1900 (Box 4)
      - Union Trust Co., 1894-1909 (Box 4)
      - Letterpress book, 1899 (Box 4)
  - Business Property, 1852-1909
    - Plat book (Newkirk), 1893-1910 (Box 4)
    - Plat book, circa 1908 (Box 4)
    - Cornell property (New York), 1852-1865 (Box 4)
    - Farnsworth subdivision; lots 38 and 39, 1885 (Box 4)
    - Ferry Land Co. (account book), 1905 (Volume 4)
    - Ferry subdivision; lots 40 and 41, 1867-1895; 7 folders (Box 4)
    - Hall-Ingersoll (future Ferry seed) farm, 1864-1904; 9 folders (Box 4)
    - Newcomb-Endicott property, 1870-1909; 8 folders (Box 4)
    - Presque Isle property, 1873-1897 (Box 4)
  - Personal papers, 1849-1911
    - Diary, 1855; typescript (Box 25)
    - Correspondence -- Dexter M. Ferry with Addie Miller, 1867; 7 folders (Box 25)
      (Addie Miller and Dexter Ferry married, October 1, 1867)
    - Correspondence-Family, 1849-1903
      - Brown family (cousins), 1864-1868 (Box 25)
      - Cornell, Joanna Mason (aunt), 1849-1856 (Box 25)
      - Crippen, Lucy D. (mother), 1852-1868; 4 folders (Box 25)
      - Ferry, Blanche (daughter), 1900 (Box 25)
      - Ferry, Dexter M., personal, 1854-1855 (Box 25)
      - Ferry, Dexter M., Jr. (son), 1893-1900 (Box 25)
      - Leavenworth, Frank (cousin), 1881-1885 (Box 25)
      - Mason, Calvin (cousin), 1858-1859 (Box 25)
      - Mason, Chloe A. (cousin), 1853-1896 (Box 25)
      - Mason, Darius (uncle), 1885-1886 (Box 25)
      - Mason, Edward (cousin), 1852-1853 (Box 25)
      - Mason, John (uncle), 1856-1868 (Box 25)
      - Mason, Persis (cousin), 1859 (Box 25)
      - Payne, Fannie (cousin), 1855 (Box 25)
      - Weeks, Augusta Ferry (sister), 1852-1903; 2 folders (Box 25)
      - Weeks, Francis Day (nephew), 1884-1893 (Box 25)
      - Weeks, William H. (brother-in-law), 1857 (Box 25)
      - White family (cousins), 1859-1867 (Box 25)
    - Correspondence-General, 1853-1899; 3 folders (Box 25)
      (include Alfred Barker, Charley Hawley, James C. Mead, George Mullinex, Ezra Parsons, James C. Parsons, and James E. Scripps)
    - Death of Dexter M. Ferry, 1907-1908
      - Condolences, 1907 (Box 25)
      - Funeral oration (DeForest), 1907 (Box 25)
      - Memorials, 1907 (Box 25)
      - Will execution, 1907-1908 (Box 25)
    - Financial papers, 1863-1911
      - Mason, Chloe (Estate of), 1898-1903 (Box 25)
      - Taxes, 1863-1909
        - Income, 1863-1900; 4 folders (Box 25)
        - Personal property, 1904-1909 (Box 25)
    - Scrapbooks, 1878-1902; 2 volumes (Box 25)
  - Philanthropic materials, 1882-1902
    - Detroit Park Commission, 1885 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous, 1885-1895 (Box 5)
    - Olivet College, 1883-1886 (Box 5)
    - University of Michigan, Ferry field, 1902 (Box 5)
    - Women's Hospital and Foundlings Home, 1882-1893 (Box 5)
    - YMCA, 1886 (Box 5)
  - Political materials, 1892-1903
    - Clippings, 1892-1900 (Box 5)
    - Correspondence, 1896-1900 (Box 5)
    - Ferry Campaign for Governor, 1900 (Box 5)
    - Campaign letterpress book, 1900 (Box 5)
    - Scrapbooks, Campaign for Republican Gubernatorial Nomination, 1899-1900; 3 volumes (Box 5)
    - Scrapbook, Republican Party State Chairman, 1896-1901 (Volume 5)
- Dexter Mason Ferry, Jr., Papers, 1881-1963
  The Dexter Mason Ferry, Jr. series comprises roughly 18 linear feet of materials arrayed in four subseries: Business, Personal, Philanthropic, and Political. The Business subseries reflects the diversification of the family's interests and consists of 5 linear feet arranged in a single alphabet. This alphabet includes firms in which Ferry had proprietary or controlling interest, and the more generic headings of: Banks and Trusts, Miscellaneous Investments, and Properties. The Personal subseries comprises 7.5 linear feet and is likewise arranged in a single alphabet according to both type of material (appointment books, correspondence, financial papers, and scrapbooks) and topic (army, education, and properties). This rather awkward arrangement was kept in order to maintain as far as possible the order created by Dexter M. Ferry, III's personal archivist. Hewing to this original order has resulted in three runs of correspondence (family, general-alphabetical, and general-chronological). The Philanthropic subseries' four feet of material range alphabetically from the Detroit Institute of Art to the University of Michigan. Within that alphabet, a diverse run of benefactors are arrayed alphabetically under Miscellaneous. The Political subseries is arranged in chronological order and comprises less than a single linear foot.
  - Business papers, 1881-1963
    - American Harrow, 1881-1925
      - Account books and minutes, 1881-1919 (Box 6)
      - Bills payable, 1919-1923 (Box 6)
      - Cashbook and ledger, 1919-1925 (Box 6)
      - Dissolution, 1914-1923; 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Stock certificates, 1902-1919 (Box 6)
      - Taxes and correspondence, 1908-1922 (Box 6)
    - Banks and Trust Companies, 1908-1955
      - Detroit Bankers Co., 1929-1932 (Box 6)
      - Detroit Trust Co., 1928-1955 (Box 6)
      - First National Bank of Detroit, 1908-1939; 3 folders (Box 6)
      - Union Trust Co., 1908-1944; 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Crosstown Garage, 1916-1939
      - General, 1916-1939 (Box 6)
      - Taxes (Detroit), 1917-1927; 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Taxes (Michigan), 1917-1927; 2 folders (Box 6)
    - D. M. Ferry & Co./Ferry-Morse Seed Co., 1899-1963
      - Histories, 1925-1963; 3 folders (Box 7)
      - Letterpress books, 1899-1908; 4 volumes (Box 7)
      - Balance sheet and list of stockholders (Box 7)
      - Report of examination (audits), 1934-1937; 1940-1943 (Box 7)
      - General (including Ferry-Morse consolidation), 1921-1959; 21 folders (Box 8)
      - Publications, 3 folders (Box 8)
    - Mesa Improvement/Consolidated Canal, 1902-1950; 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Michigan Fire and Marine Insurance Co., 1908-1958; 3 folders (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous, 1904-1959
      - Coonley Manufacturing, 1909-1939 (Box 8)
      - Development and Funding Co., 1907-1924; 2 folders (Box 8)
      - National Pin Co., 1906-1916; 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Southfield Co., 1924-1959; 3 folders (Box 8)
      - Taxes (corporate excess tax plan), 1911 (Box 8)
    - Newcomb-Endicott, 1906-1954
      - Building renovations, 1906-1910; 2 folders (Box 9)
      - Lease negotiations, 1923-1927; 2 folders (Box 9)
      - Lease agreement, 1926 (Box 9)
      - Legal Department (W. Heckman), 1908-1936 (Box 9)
      - Trust proposal, 1920-1954 (Box 9)
      - General, 1923-1945; 3 folders (Box 9)
      - Sale to J.L. Hudson, 1938-1943; 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Packard Motor Car Company, 1908-1952
      - Annual reports, 1911-1950 (Box 9)
        (transferred to printed collection)
      - General, 1908-1952 (Box 9)
      - Journal, 1909-1932 (Box 9)
    - Pilot Insurance Co., 1930-1959 (Box 9)
    - Properties, 1908-1922
      - Plat book, 1916-1920 (Box 9)
      - Balance book, 1919-1922 (Box 9)